Sméagol!
I've got one!
I've got a fish, Sméag. Sméagol!
Pull it in. Go on. Go on. Go on.
Pull it in.
Déagol!
Déagol?
Déagol.
Give us that, Déagol, my love.
Why?
Because...
...it's my birthday and I wants it.
My precious.
They cursed us.
Murderer.
"Murderer" they called us.
They cursed us
and drove us away.
Gollum.
And we wept, precious.
We wept to be so alone.
--and cool
So nice for feet
And we only wish
To catch a fish
So juicy sweet
And we forgot the taste of bread...
...the sound of trees...
...the softness of the wind.
We even forgot our own name.
My precious.
Wake up!
Wake up, sleepies.
We must go, yes.
We must go at once.
Haven't you had any sleep, Mr. Frodo?
I've gone and had too much.
Must be getting late.
No.
It isn't.
It isn't midday yet.
The days are growing darker.
Come on!
Must go! No time!
Not before Mr. Frodo's
had something to eat.
No time to lose, silly.
Here.
What about you?
Oh, no, I'm not hungry.
Leastways, not for lembas bread.
Sam.
All right.
We don't have that much left.
We have to be careful
or we're going to run out.
You go ahead and eat that, Mr. Frodo.
I've rationed it.
There should be enough.
For what?
The journey home.
Come, Hobbitses.
Very close now.
Very close to Mordor.
No safe places here.
Hurry.
It's good.
Definitely from the Shire.
Longbottom Leaf.
I feel like I'm back at
The Green Dragon.
-Green Dragon.
-A mug of ale in my hand.
Putting my feet up on a settle
after a hard day's work.
Only, you've never done
a hard day's work.
Welcome, my lords...
...to lsengard!
You young rascals!
A merry hunt you've led us on...
...and now we find you feasting
and...and smoking!
We are sitting on a field of victory...
...enjoying a few well-earned comforts.
The salted pork is particularly good.
Salted pork?
-Hobbits.
-We're under orders from Treebeard...
...who's taken over management
of lsengard.
Young Master Gandalf.
I'm glad you've come.
Wood and water, stock and stone
I can master.
But there is a wizard to manage here...
... Iocked in his tower.
Show yourself.
Be careful.
Even in defeat, Saruman is dangerous.
Well, let's just have his head
and be done with it.
No.
We need him alive.
We need him to talk.
You have fought many wars
and slain many men, Théoden King...
...and made peace afterwards.
Can we not take counsel together
as we once did, my old friend?
Can we not have peace, you and l?
We shall have peace.
We shall have peace...
...when you answer
for the burning of the Westfold...
...and the children that lie dead there!
We shall have peace
when the lives of the soldiers...
...whose bodies were hewn
even as they lay dead...
...against the gates of the Hornburg,
are avenged!
When you hang from a gibbet
for the sport of your own crows...
...we shall have peace.
Gibbets and crows?
Dotard!
What do you want, Gandalf Greyhame?
Let me guess. The Key of Orthanc.
Or perhaps the Keys of Barad-dûr itself...
...along with the crowns of the seven kings
and the rods of the Five Wizards!
Your treachery has already cost
many lives.
Thousands more are now at risk.
But you could save them, Saruman.
You were deep in the enemy's counsel.
So you have come here for information.
I have some for you.
Something festers
in the heart of Middle-earth.
Something that you have failed to see.
But the Great Eye has seen it.
Even now he presses his advantage.
His attack will come soon.
You're all going to die.
But you know this, don't you, Gandalf?
You cannot think that this Ranger
will ever sit upon the throne of Gondor.
This exile, crept from the shadows,
will never be crowned king.
Gandalf does not hesitate
to sacrifice those closest to him...
...those he professes to love.
Tell me, what words of comfort
did you give the Halfling...
...before you sent him to his doom?
The path that you have set him on
can only lead to death.
I've heard enough!
Shoot him.
Stick an arrow in his gob.
No.
Come down, Saruman...
-...and your life will be spared.
-Save your pity and your mercy.
I have no use for it!
Saruman...
...your staff is broken.
Gríma, you need not follow him.
You were not always as you are now.
You were once a Man of Rohan.
Come down.
A Man of Rohan?
What is the house of Rohan...
... but a thatched barn
where brigands drink in the reek...
...and their brats roll on the floor
with the dogs?
The victory at Helm's Deep does not
belong to you, Théoden Horse-master.
You are a lesser son of greater sires.
Gríma...
...come down.
Be free of him.
-Free? He will never be free.
-No.
Get down, cur!
Saruman!
You were deep in the enemy's counsel.
Tell us what you know!
You withdraw your guard, and I will tell you
where your doom will be decided.
I will not be held prisoner here.
Send word to all our allies...
...and to every corner of Middle-earth
that still stands free.
The enemy moves against us.
We need to know where he will strike.
The filth of Saruman...
... is washing away.
Trees will come back to live here.
Young trees.
-Wiild trees.
-Pippin!
Bless my bark!
Peregrin Took!
I'll take that, my lad.
Quickly, now.
Tonight we remember those who
gave their blood to defend this country.
Hail the victorious dead.
Hail!
No pauses.
-No spills.
-And no regurgitation.
So it's a drinking game?
Last one standing wins.
What'll we drink to?
Let's drink to victory!
To victory!
I am happy for you.
He is an honourable man.
You are both honourable men.
It was not Théoden of Rohan
who led our people to victory.
Don't listen to me.
You are young.
And tonight is for you.
Here, here.
It's the Dwarves that go swimming
with little, hairy women.
I feel something.
A slight tingle in my fingers.
I think it's affecting me.
What did I say?
He can't hold his liquor.
Game over.
Oh, you can search far and wide
You can drink the whole town dry
But you'll never find a beer so brown
As the one we drink in our hometown
You can drink your fancy ales
You can drink 'em by the flagon
But the only brew for the brave and true
Pippin!
Comes from The Green Dragon
Thank you! I win!
No news of Frodo?
No word. Nothing.
We have time.
Every day, Frodo moves closer to Mordor.
Do we know that?
What does your heart tell you?
That Frodo is alive.
Yes.
Yes, he's alive.
Too risky. Too risky.
Thieves.
They stole it from us.
Kill them. Kill them. Kill them both.
Quiet! Mustn't wake them.
Mustn't ruin it now.
But they knows.
They knows.
They suspects us.
What's it saying, my precious, my love?
Is Sméagol losing his nerve?
No. Not.
Never. Sméagol hates nasty Hobbitses.
Sméagol wants to see them dead.
And we will.
Sméagol did it once.
He can do it again.
It's ours!
Ours!
We must get the precious.
We must get it back.
Patience! Patience, my love.
First we must lead them to her.
We lead them to the Wiinding Stair.
Yes, the stairs. And then?
Up, up, up, up,
up the stairs we go...
...until we come to the tunnel.
And when they go in...
...there's no coming out.
She's always hungry.
She always needs to feed.
She must eat.
All she gets is filthy Orcses.
And they doesn't taste very nice,
does they, precious?
No.
Not very nice at all, my love.
She hungers for sweeter meats.
Hobbit meat.
And when she throws away the bones
and the empty clothes...
...then we will find it.
And take it for me!
For us.
Yes. We meant "for us."
Gollum. Gollum.
The precious will be ours...
...once the Hobbitses are dead!
You treacherous little toad!
No! No! Master!
No, Sam! Leave him alone!
I heard it from his own mouth.
He means to murder us.
Never! Sméagol wouldn't hurt a fly.
He's a horrid, fat Hobbit...
...who hates Sméagol...
...and who makes up nasty lies.
You miserable little maggot!
I'll stove your head in!
Sam!
Call me a liar? You're a liar!
-You scare him off, we're lost!
-I don't care! I can't do it, Mr. Frodo.
-I won't wait around for him to kill us!
-I'm not sending him away.
You don't see it, do you?
He's a villain.
We can't do this by ourselves, Sam.
Not without a guide.
I need you on my side.
I'm on your side, Mr. Frodo.
I know, Sam. I know.
Trust me.
Come, Sméagol.
What time is it?
Not yet dawn.
I dreamed I saw a great wave...
...climbing over green lands
and above the hills.
I stood upon the brink.
It was utterly dark in the abyss
before my feet.
A light shone behind me...
...but I could not turn.
I could only stand there, waiting.
Night changes many thoughts.
Sleep, Éowyn.
Sleep...
...while you can.
The stars are veiled.
Something stirs in the east.
A sleepless malice.
The Eye of the enemy is moving.
What are you doing?
Pippin!
Pippin?
Pippin.
-What, are you mad?
-I just want to look at it.
Just one more time.
Put it back.
Pippin.
No!
He is here.
I see you.
Pippin!
Help! Gandalf, help!
Someone help him!
Pippin!
Fool of a Took!
Look at me.
Gandalf, forgive me.
What did you see?
A tree.
There was a white tree...
...in a courtyard of stone.
It was dead.
The city was burning.
Minas Tirith? Is that what you saw?
I saw....
I saw him.
I could hear his voice in my head.
And what did you tell him?
Speak!
He asked me my name.
I didn't answer.
He hurt me.
What did you tell him
about Frodo and the Ring?
There was no lie in Pippin's eyes.
A fool...
...but an honest fool he remains.
He told Sauron nothing
of Frodo and the Ring.
We've been strangely fortunate.
Pippin saw in the palantír
a glimpse of the enemy's plan.
Sauron moves to strike
the city of Minas Tirith.
His defeat at Helm's Deep
showed our enemy one thing.
He knows the heir of Elendil
has come forth.
Men are not as weak as he supposed.
There is courage still, strength
enough perhaps to challenge him.
Sauron fears this.
He will not risk the peoples of
Middle-earth uniting under one banner.
He will raze Minas Tirith
to the ground...
...before he sees a king
return to the throne of Men.
If the beacons of Gondor are lit,
Rohan must be ready for war.
Tell me...
...why should we ride to the aid
of those who did not come to ours?
What do we owe Gondor?
-I will go.
-No!
-They must be warned.
-They will be.
You must come to Minas Tirith
by another road.
Follow the river.
Look to the black ships.
Understand this:
Things are now in motion
that cannot be undone.
I ride for Minas Tirith...
...and I won't be going alone.
Of all the inquisitive Hobbits,
Peregrin Took, you are the worst.
Hurry! Hurry!
Where are we going?
Why did you look?
Why do you always have to look?
-I don't know. I can't help it.
-You never can.
I'm sorry, all right?
-I won't do it again.
-Don't you understand?
The enemy thinks you have the Ring.
He's going to be looking for you, Pip.
They have to get you out of here.
And you--? You're coming with me?
Merry?
Come on.
How far is Minas Tirith?
Three days' ride, as the Nazgûl flies.
And you better hope we don't have
one of those on our tail.
Here.
Something for the road.
The last of the Longbottom Leaf.
I know you've run out.
You smoke too much, Pippin.
But-- But we'll see each other soon.
-Won't we?
-I don't know.
I don't know what's going to happen.
-Merry.
-Run, Shadowfax.
Show us the meaning of haste.
Merry!
He's always followed me...
...everywhere I went...
...since before we were tweens.
I would get him into
the worst sort of trouble...
...but I was always there to get him out.
Now he's gone.
Just like Frodo and Sam.
One thing I have learned about Hobbits:
They're a most hardy folk.
Foolhardy, maybe. He's a Took.
Take her by the safest road.
A ship lies anchored
in the Grey Havens.
It waits to carry her across the sea.
The last journey of Arwen Undómiel.
There is nothing for you here...
...only death.
Lady Arwen...
...we cannot delay.
My lady!
-Tell me what you have seen.
-Arwen.
You have the gift of foresight.
What did you see?
I looked into your future,
and I saw death.
But there is also life.
You saw there was a child.
You saw my son.
That future is almost gone.
But it is not lost.
Nothing is certain.
Some things are certain.
If I leave him now...
... I will regret it forever.
It is time.
From the ashes a fire shall be woken
A light from the shadow shall spring
Renewed shall be blade that was broken
The crownless again shall be king
Re-forge the sword.
Your hands are cold.
The life of the Eldar is leaving you.
This was my choice.
Whether by your will or not...
...there is no ship now
that can bear me hence.
We've just passed
into the realm of Gondor.
Minas Tirith.
City of kings.
Make way!
It's the tree.
Gandalf. Gandalf.
Yes, the White Tree of Gondor.
The tree of the king.
Lord Denethor, however,
is not king.
He is a steward only,
a caretaker of the throne.
Now listen carefully.
Lord Denethor is Boromir's father.
To give him news of his beloved son's
death would be most unwise.
And do not mention Frodo or the Ring.
And say nothing of Aragorn either.
In fact, it's better if you
don't speak at all, Peregrin Took.
Hail Denethor, son of Ecthelion,
lord and steward of Gondor.
I come with tidings in this dark hour,
and with counsel.
Perhaps you come to explain this.
Perhaps you come to tell me
why my son is dead.
Boromir died to save us...
...my kinsman and me.
-He fell defending us from many foes.
-Pippin.
I offer you my service, such as it is...
...in payment of this debt.
This is my first command to you.
How did you escape
and my son did not...
...so mighty a man as he was?
The mightiest man
may be slain by one arrow...
...and Boromir was pierced by many.
Get up.
My lord, there will be a time
to grieve for Boromir...
...but it is not now.
War is coming.
The enemy is on your doorstep.
As steward, you are charged...
...with the defense of this city.
Where are Gondor's armies?
You still have friends.
You are not alone in this fight.
Send word to Théoden of Rohan.
Light the beacons.
You think you are wise, Mithrandir.
Yet for all your subtleties,
you have not wisdom.
Do you think the eyes
of the White Tower are blind?
I have seen more than you know.
Wiith your left hand you would use me
as a shield against Mordor.
And with your right
you'd seek to supplant me.
I knowwho rides with Théoden of Rohan.
Oh, yes. Word has reached my ears
of this Aragorn, son of Arathorn.
And I tell you now, I will not bow
to this Ranger from the North...
... Iast of a ragged house
long bereft of lordship.
Authority is not given to you
to deny the return of the king, steward.
The rule of Gondor is mine
and no other's.
Come.
All has turned to vain ambition.
He would even use his grief
as a cloak.
A thousand years
this city has stood.
Now, at the whim of a madman,
it will fall.
And the White Tree,
the tree of the king...
...will never bloom again.
-Why are they still guarding it?
-They guard it because they have hope.
A faint and fading hope
that one day it will flower.
That a king will come
and this city will be as it once was...
... before it fell into decay.
The old wisdom borne out
of the West was forsaken.
Kings made tombs more splendid
than the houses of the living...
...and counted the old names
of their descent...
...dearer than the names of their sons.
Childless lords sat in aged halls,
musing on heraldry...
...or in high, cold towers,
asking questions of the stars.
And so the people of Gondor
fell into ruin.
The line of kings failed.
The White Tree withered.
The rule of Gondor was given over
to lesser men.
Mordor.
Yes, there it lies.
This city has dwelt ever
in the sight of its shadow.
A storm is coming.
This is not the weather of the world.
This is a device of Sauron's making.
A broil of fume
he sends ahead of his host.
The Orcs of Mordor
have no love of daylight...
...so he covers the face of the sun...
...to ease their passage
along the road to war.
When the Shadow of Mordor
reaches this city...
...it will begin.
Well...
... Minas Tirith...
...very impressive.
-So where are we off to next?
-Oh, it's too late for that, Peregrin.
There's no leaving this city.
Help must come to us.
It must be getting near teatime.
Leastways, it would be in decent places
where there is still teatime.
We're not in decent places.
Mr. Frodo?
What is it?
It's just a feeling.
I don't think I'll be coming back.
Yes, you will. Of course you will.
That's just morbid thinking.
We're going there and back again...
...just like Mr. Bilbo.
You'll see.
I think these lands were once
part of the kingdom of Gondor.
Long ago, when there was a king.
Mr. Frodo, look.
The king has got a crown again.
Come on, Hobbits!
Mustn't stop now. This way.
So I imagine this is just
a ceremonial position.
I mean, they don't actually expect me
to do any fighting.
-Do they?
-You're in the service of the steward now.
You'll have to do as you're told,
Peregrin Took.
Ridiculous Hobbit.
Guard of the Citadel.
Thank you.
There's no more stars.
Is it time?
Yes.
It's so quiet.
It's the deep breath before the plunge.
I don't want to be in a battle...
... but waiting on the edge of one
I can't escape is even worse.
Is there any hope, Gandalf,
for Frodo and Sam?
There never was much hope.
Just a fool's hope.
Our enemy is ready.
His full strength's gathered.
Not only Orcs, but Men as well.
Legions of Haradrim from the south...
...mercenaries from the coast.
All will answer Mordor's call.
Come on.
This will be the end of Gondor
as we know it.
Here the hammer stroke will fall hardest.
If the river is taken,
if the garrison at Osgiliath falls...
...the last defense of this city
will be gone.
But we have the White Wiizard.
That's got to count for something.
Gandalf?
Sauron has yet to reveal
his deadliest servant...
...the one who will lead
Mordor's armies in war.
The one they say no living man can kill.
The Wiitch King of Angmar.
You've met him before.
He stabbed Frodo on Weathertop.
He is the lord of the Nazgûl...
...the greatest of the Nine.
Minas Morgul is his lair.
The Dead City.
Very nasty place. Full of enemies.
Quick. Quick.
They will see. They will see.
Come away. Come away.
Look, we have found it.
The way into Mordor.
The secret stair.
Climb.
-No, Mr. Frodo!
-Not that way!
-What's it doing?
-No.
-They're calling me.
Hide! Hide!
I can feel his blade.
We come to it at last.
The great battle of our time.
Come away, Hobbits.
We climb. We must climb.
The board is set.
The pieces are moving.
Up, up, up the stairs we go.
And then it's into the tunnel.
Hey, what's in this tunnel?
You listen to me,
and you listen good and proper.
Anything happens to him,
you have me to answer to.
One sniff something's not right...
...one hair stands up
on the back of my head, it's over.
No more slinker. No more stinker.
You're gone. Got it?
I'm watching you.
What was that about?
Nothing. Just clearing something up.
Peregrin Took, my lad,
there is a task now to be done.
Another opportunity for one
of the Shire-folk to prove their great worth.
You must not fail me.
It's been very quiet across the river.
The Orcs are lying low.
The garrison may have moved out.
We've sent scouts to Cair Andros.
If the Orcs attack from the north,
we'll have some warning.
Quiet.
We need 1 0 more.
Kill him!
They're not coming from the north.
To the river. Quick. Quick.
Go. Come on.
Faster.
Draw swords.
Hold! Hold them!
What?
Amon Dîn.
The beacon.
The beacon of Amon Dîn is lit.
Hope is kindled.
The beacons of Minas Tirith!
The beacons are lit!
Gondor calls for aid.
And Rohan will answer.
Muster the Rohirrim.
Assemble the army at Dunharrow.
As many men as can be found.
You have two days.
On the third,
we ride for Gondor and war.
-Forward.
-Very good, sir.
-Gamling.
-My lord.
Make haste
across the Riddermark.
Summon every able-bodied man
to Dunharrow.
I will.
-Wiill you ride with us?
-Just to the encampment.
It's tradition for the women
of the court to farewell the men.
The men have found their captain.
They will follow you into battle,
even to death.
You have given us hope.
Excuse me.
I have a sword.
Please accept it.
I offer you my service, Théoden King.
And gladly I accept it.
You shall be Meriadoc,
esquire of Rohan.
Horse-Men.
I wish I could muster a legion of Dwarves,
fully armed and filthy.
Your kinsmen may have no need
to ride to war.
I fear war already marches
on their own lands.
So it is before the walls
of Minas Tirith...
...the doom of our time will be decided.
Now is the hour.
Riders of Rohan, oaths you have taken.
Now, fulfill them all.
To lord and land!
Faramir!
We can't hold them. The city is lost.
Tell the men to break cover.
We ride for Minas Tirith.
Nazgûl.
Take cover!
Nazgûl!
Fall back. Fall back to Minas Tirith!
Fall back!
-Retreat! Retreat!
-Run for your lives!
The age of Men is over.
The time of the Orc has come.
-Keep going.
-It's the Nazgûl.
Take cover, my lord!
It's coming!
-It's Mithrandir.
-The White Rider!
Pull!
Mithrandir.
They broke through our defenses.
They've taken the bridge
and the west bank.
-Battalions of Orcs are crossing the river.
-lt is as the Lord Denethor predicted.
-Long has he foreseen this doom.
-Foreseen and done nothing.
Faramir?
This is not the first Halfling
to have crossed your path.
No.
You've seen Frodo and Sam?
-Where? When?
-ln lthilien.
Not two days ago.
Gandalf, they're taking the road
to the Morgul Vale.
And then the pass of Cirith Ungol.
What does that mean?
-What's wrong?
-Faramir, tell me everything.
Tell me all you know.
This is how you would serve your city?
You would risk its utter ruin?
I did what I judged to be right.
What you judged to be right.
You sent the Ring of Power into Mordor
in the hands of a witless Halfling.
It should have been brought back
to the Citadel to be kept safe.
Hidden.
Dark and deep in the vaults...
... not to be used.
Unless at the uttermost end of need.
I would not use the Ring.
Not if Minas Tirith were falling in ruin
and I alone could save her.
Ever you desire to appear lordly
and gracious...
...as a king of old.
Boromir would have remembered
his father's need.
He would have brought me a kingly gift.
Boromir would not
have brought the Ring.
He would have stretched out his hand to
this thing and taken it. He would've fallen.
-You know nothing of this matter!
-He would have kept it for his own.
And when he returned...
...you would not have known your son.
Boromir was loyal to me!
Not some wizard's pupil!
Father?
My son.
Leave me.
Careful, master. Careful.
Very far to fall.
Very dangerous are the stairs.
Come, master.
Come to Sméagol.
Mr. Frodo.
Get back, you!
Don't touch him!
Why does he hates poor Sméagol?
What has Sméagol ever done to him?
Master?
Master carries heavy burden.
Sméagol knows.
Heavy, heavy burden.
Fat one cannot know.
Sméagol look after master.
He wants it.
He needs it.
Sméagol sees it in his eye.
Very soon he will ask you for it.
You will see.
The fat one will take it from you.
Send forth all legions.
Do not stop the attack
until the city is taken.
Slay them all.
-What of the wizard?
-I will break him.
Where are Théoden's riders?
Wiill Rohan's army come?
Mithrandir.
Courage is the best defense
that you have now.
What were you thinking, Peregrin Took?
What service can a Hobbit
offer such a great lord of Men?
It was well-done.
A generous deed should not
be checked with cold counsel.
You are to join the tower guard.
I didn't think they would find any livery
that would fit me.
Once belonged to a young boy
of the city.
A very foolish one...
...who wasted many hours slaying dragons
instead of attending to his studies.
-This was yours?
-Yes, it was mine.
My father had it made for me.
Well...
... I'm taller than you were then.
Though I'm not likely to grow anymore,
except sideways.
Never fitted me either.
Boromir was always the soldier.
They were so alike, he and my father.
Proud.
Stubborn even.
But strong.
I think you have strength
of a different kind.
And one day your father will see it.
Here do I swear fealty
and service to Gondor...
... in peace or war...
...in living or dying...
...from....
From this hour henceforth...
... until my lord release me...
...or death take me.
And I shall not forget it...
...nor fail to reward
that which is given.
Fealty with love.
Valour with honour.
Disloyalty with vengeance.
I do not think we should so lightly
abandon the outer defenses...
...defenses that your brother
long held intact.
-What would you have me do?
-I will not yield...
...the river in Pelennor unfought.
Osgiliath must be retaken.
My lord, Osgiliath is overrun.
Much must be risked in war.
Is there a captain here who still has
the courage to do his lord's will?
You wish now that our places
had been exchanged...
...that I had died
and Boromir had lived.
Yes.
I wish that.
Since you were robbed
of Boromir...
... I will do what I can
in his stead.
If I should return,
think better of me, Father.
That will depend on the manner
of your return.
What are you up to?
Sneaking off, are we?
Sneaking?
Fat Hobbit is always so polite.
Sméagol shows them secret ways
that nobody else could find...
...and they say "sneak."
Sneak?
Very nice friend.
Oh, yes, my precious.
-Very nice, very nice.
-All right. All right!
You just startled me is all.
What were you doing?
Sneaking.
Fine. Have it your own way.
I'm sorry to wake you, Mr. Frodo.
We have to be moving on.
It's dark still.
It's always dark here.
It's gone!
-The Elven bread.
-What?
That's all we have left.
He took it. He must have!
Sméagol?
No, no, not poor Sméagol.
Sméagol hates nasty Elf bread.
You're a lying rat!
What did you do with it?!
He doesn't eat it.
-He can't have taken it.
-Look.
What's this?
Crumbs on his jacketses.
He took it!
He took it.
I seen him. He's always stuffing
his face when master's not looking.
That's a filthy lie!
You stinking, two-faced sneak!
-Sam!
-Call me--
Stop it!
Sam!
-I'll kill him!
-Sam! No!
Oh, my-- I'm sorry. I didn't mean it
to go so far. I was just so-- So angry.
Here, just--
Let's just rest a bit.
-I'm all right.
-No.
No, you're not all right.
You're exhausted.
It's that Gollum.
It's this place.
It's that thing around your neck.
I could help a bit.
I could carry it for a while.
Carry it for a while.
I could carry it... I could carry it.
Share the load...Share the load...
the load...the load.
Get away!
I don't want to keep it.
I just want to help.
See? See?
He wants it for himself.
Shut up, you!
Go away!
Get out of here!
No, Sam.
It's you.
I'm sorry, Sam.
But he's a liar.
He's poisoned you against me.
You can't help me anymore.
You don't mean that.
Go home.
Faramir!
Your father's will has turned
to madness.
Do not throw away your life
so rashly.
Where does my allegiance lie
if not here?
This is the city of the Men of Númenor.
I will gladly give my life
to defend her beauty...
...her memory, her wisdom.
Your father loves you, Faramir.
He will remember it
before the end.
Can you sing, Master Hobbit?